<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A breif [sic] enquiry into the ground, authority, and rights, of ecclesiastical synods; upon the principles of Scripture and right reason occasion'd by a late book, intitul'd, Municipium ecclesiasticum: &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 52 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2005B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R178160</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077507</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077507</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151570</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86352)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151570)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2265:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A breif [sic] enquiry into the ground, authority, and rights, of ecclesiastical synods; upon the principles of Scripture and right reason occasion'd by a late book, intitul'd, Municipium ecclesiasticum: &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716.</author>
                  <author>Hill, Samuel, 1648-1716. Municipium ecclesiasticum, or, The rights, liberties, and authorities of the Christian church.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.B. for Richard Sare, at Gray's-Inn-Gate, in Holbourn,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title within double line border.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Samuel Hill by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [1] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Trinity College Library, Dublin, Ireland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wake, William, 1657-1737. --  Authority of Christian princes over their ecclesiastical synods asserted.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151570:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151570:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Breif Enquiry INTO THE Ground, Authority, and Rights, OF <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Synods;</hi> Upon the Principles of SCRIPTURE, AND Right Reaſon: Occaſion'd by a Late BOOK, INTITUL'D, <hi>Municipium Eccleſiaſticum:</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. B.</hi> for <hi>Richard Sare,</hi> at <hi>Gray's-Inn-Gate,</hi> in <hi>Holbourn.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151570:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151570:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Reverend Dr. <hi>Wake,</hi> in his Book Intitul'd, <hi>The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Chriſtian Princes over their Eccleſiaſtical Synods aſſerted,</hi> &amp;c. has chiefly argued from matters of Fact, in thoſe Inſtances of Power and Juriſdiction, which have, all along, been claimed and exerciſed by Chriſtian Emperours and Kings (except only where the unjuſt En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croachments of the Papacy, had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt the Lawful Right of
<pb facs="tcp:151570:3"/>the Civil Magiſtrate) and which, by the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> are actually annexed to the Imperial Crown of the Realm. Now if the Hiſtorical account, which he has given of this matter, be defective; let it be ſhewn either that his Quotations are falſe, or elſe inſufficient. But if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe can be done, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how any one, who has ſubſcrib'd to the Second Canon of our Church, can deny <hi>The King's Majeſty</hi> to have <hi>the ſame Authority, in Cauſes Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical,</hi> as the Doctor has proved <hi>the Chriſtian Emperours</hi> to have had, <hi>in the Primitive Church:</hi> But much more do I admire, that ſuch a man ſhould venture <hi>to impeach in any part the Regal Supremacy, in the ſaid Cauſes Reſtored to the Crown; and by the Laws of the Realm therein eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151570:3"/>
            <p> But ſuppoſing a man to pay no deference to the Authority of our Church, nor yet to the Opinions of our moſt learned Divines; many of which the Doctor has Collected in his <hi>Appeal to all true members of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in the behalf of the Kings Eccleſiaſtical Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> there is one plauſible Objection that may be made againſt his Book; and is earneſtly urged by the Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Author of the <hi>Municipium Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticum,</hi> Chap. x. <hi>viz.</hi> That to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue a <hi>right</hi> in any one, from bare <hi>Matter of Fact alone,</hi> is by no means a ſufficient or concluſive way of Reaſoning: And therefore to take off this prejudice, I think it would be a very neceſſary and uſeful work, to give a clear and ſatisfactory ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, of the <hi>Ground, Authority</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:151570:4"/>
               <hi>Rights of Eccleſiaſtical Synods,</hi> from the Law of God, and Reaſon of things; Whereby it might plainly be made appear, whether or no that Power which other Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces have exerciſed, and our Kings do claim and practiſe over them; be built upon a good Foundation; or elſe be only an Encroachment and Uſurpation upon the Church.</p>
            <p>What the <hi>Municipium Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> advances, upon this ſubject, to me ſeems very obſcure and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: And whether the fault be in the Book, or in my Underſtanding, I know not; but I muſt own that I am not able to frame ſufficiently clear and diſtinct notions of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Opinions, or the force of his Arguments, in reference to this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which he profeſſedly propoſes to
<pb facs="tcp:151570:4"/>handle. And altho' Dr. <hi>Wake</hi> has here and there ſome very uſeful hints upon this ſubject; yet as they are not all laid together in one part of his Book, ſo neither perhaps would they amount to, nor were they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, a juſt diſcourſe upon this Argument: Which therefore I could heartily wiſh that he would ſet him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to write; as being well aſſured, by what I have read of his other works, that he is abundantly able to give ſatisfaction to all reaſonable men, in whatſoever he ſhall think fit to undertake.</p>
            <p>To provoke, therefore, either him, or ſome other Learned man, to ſet upon this work; I have drawn up the following ſhort Eſſay; in which I have very freely and plainly ſet down my own thoughts; And
<pb facs="tcp:151570:5"/>wherever I may happen to be in the wrong; I ſhall own my ſelf much obliged unto any Charitable hand that ſhall endeavour again to ſet me right.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151570:5"/>
            <head>AN ESSAY Concerning <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Synods.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. BY an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Synod,</hi> I mean, <hi>a Lawful Aſſembly, either of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops alone; or of one or more Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in conjunction with ſome Presbyters of the Church; or,</hi> Laſtly, <hi>of Presbyters alone; duly and ſufficiently Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riz'd to conſult and determine ſome matter, relating to the good of the Church, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Religion; ſo as that others ſhall be oblig'd to ſubmit, and give Obedience, to their Decrees and Determinations.</hi> For tho' <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons,</hi> or <hi>Lay Perſons,</hi> may, in ſome caſes, be admitted to aſſemble with the others in a Synod; Yet I take it for granted, that their abſence makes it never the leſs, or their preſence the more, a Synod; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing it to have all the other qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And if ſuch an Aſſembly be not
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151570:6"/>
               <hi>Lawful;</hi> that is to ſay <hi>Juſtifiable by ſome ſufficient Law;</hi> it would rather be a <hi>Rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous,</hi> or <hi>Schiſmatical Meeting,</hi> than an <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Synod.</hi> And if the Biſhops or Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, when met together, have not <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Authority</hi> to tranſact matters, and lay an Obligation upon others, as is above ſaid; they can, at moſt be ſaid to be but a <hi>Prudential Aſſembly.</hi> And Laſtly if they meet upon other buſineſs, wherein the <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> are not concern'd; Notwithſtanding that the Perſons who compoſe the Aſſembly may be all <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticks,</hi> yet ſuch an Aſſembly, I conceive can not ſo properly be call'd <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. From the different extent of that tract, or diſtrict, of the Church, from whence, and for which, any Synod is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened; It may take and derive to it ſelf a different denomination. Thus, for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample; If a Synod be call'd from within ſo much of the Church only, as is under the care and Government but of one Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, It is call'd a <hi>Dioceſan Synod:</hi> If from within ſeveral Dioceſſes, more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly conſociated under the juriſdiction of one Metropolitan, a <hi>Provincial Synod:</hi> If from all the ſeveral Provinces of one Kingdom or People, a <hi>National Synod:</hi> And if from every part of the whole
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151570:6"/>Church, a <hi>General</hi> or <hi>Oecumenical Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Concerning <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Synods,</hi> I ſhall propoſe Four things to be inquired into: Firſt, <hi>Of what Inſtitution they are in the Chriſtian Church: viz.</hi> Whether of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine or Human? Secondly, <hi>What right they have to meet and act, antecedent to the Civil Laws of each Kingdom or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth?</hi> Thirdly, <hi>In what things, and over whom, they may have Authority?</hi> (I mean ſtill antecedent to the Civil Laws) And Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>How far their right of Meeting and Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or their Authority over others, may be reſtrained, limited, or qualified, by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of the Church to the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, or otherwiſe by the Laws of any King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or Commonwealth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Towards the anſwering the Firſt Inquiry; Let it be noted, that to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> of any Aſſembly it is abſolutely neceſſary that there be ſome <hi>certain Rule</hi> for the fixing and determining, at the leaſt, theſe three things; <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, <hi>At what time, and place, they ſhall meet;</hi> Secondly, <hi>Of what Perſons the Aſſembly ſhall be compos'd;</hi> And Thirdly, <hi>What they are to do when they come together.</hi> For while any one of theſe things remain uncertain, the Aſſembly can not be ſaid to be <hi>Inſtituted</hi> or <hi>Appointed.</hi> For Firſt, if the time or place of Meeting
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151570:7"/>be undetermined; ſome of the Members may come at one time, and to one place, and ſome at, and to, another; and ſo either return again for want of Buſineſs to be done; Or elſe form themſelves into many little <hi>Junctos</hi> inſtead of one <hi>Aſſembly.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, if it be not known who the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are that are to make up the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; Either all men may abſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo there will be no Aſſembly at all; Or elſe they who are altogether unqualified for ſuch a Meeting, may yet croud in; And ſo inſtead of an Aſſembly become a confuſed multitude. And Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if when they are met together they know not what they are to do; As their meeting will be altogether uſeleſs and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent; ſo can they not, in my opinion, be juſtly called an <hi>Inſtituted Aſſembly;</hi> The very Notion of which, in my apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, implies a Company of Men choſen and met together, <hi>For the diſpatch of ſome Buſineſs,</hi> either known to them before hand, or elſe to be Communicated to them at the time of their meeting. If then either the ſtanding Law of God, or any occaſional Command of his, has any where required, Firſt, that in the Chriſtian Church, Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies ſhall meet at ſuch a certain time, and place, either appointed by God himſelf, or to be appointed by ſome certain Perſon
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151570:7"/>or Perſons, having Power from God to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the ſame: And Secondly that ſuch Aſſemblies ſhall conſiſt principally, if not only, of the Biſhops or Presbyters of the Church; And Thirdly that their Buſineſs, when they meet, ſhall be to conſult, and to determine certain matters relating to the good of the Church, and benefit of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; in ſuch Wiſe as that others ſhall be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blig'd to ſubmit, and give Obedience, to their decrees and determinations; Then indeed it will be moſt evident that Eccleſiaſtical <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods</hi> (according to the Definition laid down §. 1.) are of Divine Inſtitution. But if, on the other ſide, it appears that theſe three things are no other way enacted and determined, ſave only, at firſt, by the volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary agreement of the Church, and, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, by its ſetled and eſtabliſh'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions; And laſt of all by the Laws and Conſtitutions of the ſeveral Chriſtian Kingdoms and States in the World; Then it will no leſs plainly appear that Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Synods are not of Divine, but Human Inſtitution. Or, Laſtly, If it be found that theſe ſame things are ſetled and fixed, partly by the Law or Command of God, and partly by human Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Laws, and Conſtitutions; Then it muſt follow that the Inſtitution of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Synods, is partly Divine, and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151570:8"/>Human. And having thus, I think, plainly ſtated the Caſe, and propoſed the Iſſue to be tried, upon the firſt Inquiry; I ſhall proceed to Conſider, what ſolid Foundation may be had, upon which to build a ſound and determinate judgement in the matter.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And Firſt That <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Synods</hi> (whether Dioceſan, Provincial, National, or General) <hi>are not purely, and altogether, of Divine Inſtitution,</hi> I take to be a thing moſt evident: There being neither any ſtanding Law, nor occaſional Command of God (that appears) which either requires that any ſuch Aſſemblies ſhall meet; or gives Authority to any one to appoint the time, and place, of their meeting; or ſets down the qualifications of ſuch Perſons as are to make up the Aſſembly; Or, Laſtly, declares what power they have (or that they have any at all) to determine any matter, ſo as to lay an Obligation upon other Men, to ſubmit to their Decrees or Definitions. See §. 5.</p>
            <p n="6">6. But here perhaps it may be objected, that the Chriſtian Church is a <hi>Society;</hi> that the very nature of a <hi>Society</hi> ſuppoſes <hi>Order</hi> and <hi>Government;</hi> and that theſe do as neceſſarily require <hi>Deliberation</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultation;</hi> that is to ſay debating and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining ſuch difficulties as may occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onally
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151570:8"/>ariſe: And as theſe things cannot be duly performed without the meeting of regular Aſſemblies; ſo is it not in the leaſt to be doubted, but that the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church (who on all hands are allowed to be under Chriſt the Rulers and Governours of it) ought, if not ſolely, yet cheifly, to compoſe and make up ſuch Aſſemblies; Which therefore muſt be <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Synods,</hi> according to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finition of them laid down by me §. 1. Now altho' to all this I need make no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, becauſe it does not Anſwer what I have Urged; but wholly (in a manner) waves and leaves it behind: Yet becauſe I do not deſire to avoid any difficulty, without giving full ſatisfaction to it; I ſhall very freely ſet down my Thoughts in relation to what is here alleged; Being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ready either to alter or retract them, whenſoever I ſhall be convinced of any miſtake in Them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the Chriſtian Church then is a Society, I readily grant; as alſo that a Society cannot be, that is to ſay cannot ſubſiſt and continue, without Order and Government: But then it does not follow that the ſame Perſon, who Inſtitutes a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety, muſt neceſſarily appoint the compleat Model of its Government. But it may be ſufficient for him to determine and propoſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151570:9"/>the end for which they are aſſociated; and preſcribe all thoſe Laws that are abſolutely neceſſary for the obtaining of that end; And when that is done to leave the Society to their own prudence, to regulate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into ſuch a certain frame of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as they find may be moſt fit and proper for the purſuing that end, for which they are Incorporated, according to thoſe Laws which their Firſt Founder has given them. Thus (for Example) it is poſſible that the King, may erect a Company or Corporation, for the carrying on of ſuch a certain Negotiation: And as long as They purſue the end for which they are thus Embodyed, and obſerve the Laws of the Land, and ſuch other neceſſary directions as are given them at their Erection; It is no manner of abſurdity to ſuppoſe that they may be left to their own liberty, among themſelves, to appoint and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine who, and what, and how many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and under what limitations and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, ſhall have the Government and Managment of the affairs of the Society; in Subordination ſtill to the Laws of the Civil State, and the Authority of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate. Thus likewiſe I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it will eaſily be granted, that by the Law of Nature, which is the Law of God, all mankind in general are <hi>a Society;</hi> that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151570:9"/>is to ſay, <hi>a number of Perſons under, an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation mutually to help, and be aſſiſtant each to other, in the promoting and carrying on ſome certain End and Deſign,</hi> viz. The general welfare of all and every Man. Now that this Society (as all others) cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Government, be duly maintained and kept up, muſt likewiſe be granted. But yet it is plain, that neither the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, nor any other Law of God, has ſetled or determin'd any certain Frame or Model of Government, either for the whole World in general, or for each Kingdom or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth in particular: But as long as Men Swerve not from the Laws of God, and that general deſign, which he, by the Principles of Reaſon, and more fully by Revelation, has made known unto us; 'tis certain that he forbids them not, but leaves them at their own liberty to form themſelves into ſuch Civil Communities, and to erect ſuch Forms and Schemes of Government among themſelves, as they, in their own prudence, ſhall think fit to agree upon. In like manner, that the Church is a Society, Inſtituted by Chriſt, for the promoting of God's Glory and the Salvation of mankind; That He has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven divers Laws and Directions to this Society; And that, for the better obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and enforcing of theſe Directions
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151570:10"/>and Laws, Order and Government is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in the Church; are things by no means to be denyed or gainſaid: But that God has laid down any <hi>compleat and exact model of Eccleſiaſtical Government,</hi> either for the whole Church in general; or for the parts of it (as Nations or Kingdoms) in particular, is what I can no where find; But ſhould be very glad, if it be really ſo, to ſee ſuch clear and evident proof thereof as may ſafely be relied on. Altho' there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it may be granted that all Chriſtians in general; and, in particular, the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church, are under an Obligation, as they have opportunity, and as occaſion ſhall call upon them; to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate and conſult about ſuch things, as may moſt conduce to the promoting of the great end and deſign of Chriſtianity; and, in order thereunto, to have ſuch Meetings as they apprehend may be moſt ſerviceable to this purpoſe (to which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every good Chriſtian ought for his part to conſent, and, as much as lies in him, to concurr) yet how any <hi>certain Form,</hi> or Preſcript, of Eccleſiaſtical Synods; either General, National, Provincial, or Dioceſan, duly inveſted with Authority, can from hence be inferred, without any farther hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man appointment, I cannot in the leaſt ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine. And however a man may put a
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151570:10"/>ſpecious and plauſible gloſs upon the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet to affirm that Eccleſiaſtical Synods are of Divine Inſtitution; without aſſigning any Law or Command of God, either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, or elſe by good conſequence, to make good thoſe particulars that I have but now denyed §. 5. muſt I think, upon a through examination, be found moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd and unreaſonable.</p>
            <p n="8">8. But, it may be, it will be farther objected that it is beyond diſpute, that the Apoſtles did hold Eccleſiaſtical Synods: And therefore we may well preſume that there was a Command for this, altho' we do not find it recorded expreſly in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scriptures. To which I anſwer; that I do indeed allow that the Apoſtles, with ſome Others, did ſometimes meet together for the determining and ſetling of ſome things, which related to the good of the Church, and Benefit of Religion: <hi>Act.</hi> 1.15. and 6.2. and 15.6. And therefore I will not ſay but that they did, or might have held Eccleſiaſtical Synods. But why muſt we ſuppoſe that they had a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Command from God for the doing of that, which common Prudence and natural Reaſon, muſt needs ſuggeſt to all ſober men in the like circumſtances? Or if they had any ſpecial Command from God for the holding any of thoſe Meetings (which
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151570:11"/>yet is more than we can tell) I cannot ſee how ſuch an unrecorded, and Unknown Command, can ever be reckoned as a ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perpetual Rule to the Church.</p>
            <p n="9">9. Secondly, Altho' there is no manner of Divine Inſtitution, Properly ſpeaking; Yet I freely allow that, <hi>in the Law of God and the Reaſon of things, there is a very good</hi> prudential Foundation <hi>for Eccleſiaſtical Synods.</hi> That is to ſay, that ſuch things are ſuggeſted unto us, partly by God's Law, and partly by natural Reaſon; as muſt needs convince every ſober and thinking man, that it is highly conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that, upon ſome occaſions, Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Synods ſhould be convened and holden. For as the Law of God obliges every man to do as much good as he is able, in his place and ſtation; and to promote the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God and the Salvation of all men, as far as he has, or can procure, opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, for ſo doing; ſo does our own Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſufficiently aſſure us that theſe things may, upon many occaſions, be expedited and ſet forward, and free from ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and impediments as too often do ariſe; much better by the joint and unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous endeavours of many wiſe and good men concurring together, than by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and ſeparate labour of each of thoſe men ſeverally and apart: As alſo that no
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151570:11"/>men ordinarily can be ſuppoſed to be more fit to handle, judge, and determine, whatever relates to matters of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, than they who have made theſe very things, their chiefeſt care and Buſineſs; that is to ſay than the Biſhops and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church. Whenever there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any doubt or difficulty ariſes about any thing, wherein the Glory of God, and the Salvation of Men are concerned; which cannot more readily or eaſily be aſſoiled and removed; Nothing, I think, can be more proper and rational, than that a convenient number of the Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church ſhould be aſſembled together, in order to conſult and declare their Senſe and Judgement in the Caſe. And becauſe ſuch Aſſemblies would ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie little or nothing, if every Man were ſtill left at his Liberty, either to give or refuſe Submiſſion to their Determinations; It is therefore very proper that all thoſe Men, for whoſe ſake, and upon whoſe account, the Aſſembly meets, ſhould be under ſome obligation to acquieſce in, and be obedient unto, ſuch things as are there Concluded upon and Decreed: The ground and extent of which Obligation ſhall be inquired into in its proper place. And this I take to be a fair and rational Account of, and Foundation for, the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151570:12"/>and holding of Eccleſiaſtical Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods; But by no means to denominate them <hi>of Divine Inſtitution,</hi> any more than Parliaments, or any other Aſſemblies, which are held for the promoting of the temporal welfare and happineſs of men; to the forwarding of which every man is as <hi>really</hi> (tho' perhaps not as <hi>highly</hi>) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged by the Law of God, as he is to advance the glory of God, or promote the Salvation of others.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Thirdly, altho' I will not take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to determine whether the Apoſtles had any immediate Command from God, for the holding of any of thoſe Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies (or Synods as ſome will have them to be) of which we but juſt now were ſpeaking §. 8. which for ought I know, they might; or whether therein they fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed only the Dictates of common pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; which, as far as I can judge is altogether as probable as the other: Yet, untill I ſhall ſee ſome better reaſon to the contrary; I cannot but think that, <hi>From the time of the Apoſtles downwards, All the Eccleſiaſtical Synods, that ever have been held in the Church, have been purely and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together of human Inſtitution.</hi> Altho' (as I have ſaid in the preceeding Section) there may have been a prudential Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation for them in the Law of God, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151570:12"/>the reaſon of things; As indeed there is for Parliaments or ſuch ſort of Aſſemblies in the State, as well as for Synods in the Church. For if no other Rule or Law can be found (excepting only firſt the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Agreement of the Church it ſelf, and afterwards the Laws of Civil States when they became Chriſtian) either firſt for the calling of any ſuch Aſſemblies at all; Or the appointing of time or place for their meeting; Or ſecondly for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing and determining who and what Perſons ſhall compoſe them; Or Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the empowering them to Act, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliging others to ſubmit to them; Then it muſt follow that they are purely and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together of Human Inſtitution; Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what I have laid down §. 4. But no other Law or Rule for any of theſe things did ever yet appear to me, upon the moſt impartial ſearch that I have been able to make: And therefore I cannot judge them to be of any other Inſtitution than what I have already ſaid. And let thus much ſuffice for the firſt Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p n="11">11. As to the Second Enquiry, <hi>viz. What right Eccleſiaſtical Synods have to meet and Act antecedent to the Laws of each Kingdom and Commonwealth:</hi> By <hi>a right to do any thing</hi> I underſtand, not only a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151570:13"/>Natural, but, <hi>ſuch a</hi> Moral Power <hi>of perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch an Action, as that it would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for another man to hinder or obſtruct the ſame.</hi> Thus every man has a <hi>Right</hi> to make uſe of thoſe things, which he has honeſtly gotten, for the preſerving and ſuſtaining of his own Life; And alſo to worſhip God according as he has appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in order to his own Salvation: Nor can it (at leaſt ordinarily) be Lawful for any man to debar, or prohibit another in, or from the doing of either of theſe things. Let us then but ſet our Selves to enquire how far, and in what caſes, it may be ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lawful or Unlawful for any Perſons to hinder an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Synod</hi> from Act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Meeting; And this will lead us to an exact knowledge of their Right to Meet and Act; together with the juſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and meaſure of it.</p>
            <p n="12">12. In the firſt place then. <hi>Where any Perſons meet together in order to do good; And it alſo ſufficiently appears that there is no probability of any evil Conſequence of their meeting; Such an Aſſembly as this ought not upon any account, or by any one, either to be prohibited or diſturbed.</hi> For as every man is under an obligation, himſelf, to do all the good which he has an opportunity for; ſo ought he not (by parity of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) to be any hindrance to any other men
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:151570:13"/>in their doing whatever good may lie in their power.</p>
            <p n="13">13. But, Secondly, <hi>Wherever there is a juſt and well grounded Suſpicion, that ſuch a Meeting or Aſſembly will prove,</hi> in the end, <hi>to be of Evil Conſequence</hi> (However well it may perhaps, by ſome, be deſigned;) <hi>As far as any Perſon or Perſons lie under an Obligation to prevent the Evil that is ſo juſtly beforehand ſuſpected, ſo far are they obliged to hinder, as much as they can, the Convening of ſuch an Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly:</hi> I mean upon a ſuppoſition that the Evil Conſequence is not by any other way to be avoided. This I take to be as plain as any thing almoſt can be. And therefore if the Civil Magiſtrate, according to the beſt of his Underſtanding, foreſees and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves that the meeting of any Aſſembly (altho' upon the deſign and buſineſs of Religion) will probably create feuds and animoſities among the People, or keep up and heighten thoſe which are already rais'd, which in the end may tend to Fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Diviſion in the Church or State; As he is obliged, by the Truſt repoſed in him, to preſerve and maintain Peace and quietneſs, and good order in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth; ſo will it Conſequently be his Duty, as far as he is Inveſted with Lawful Power for it, to prevent and put a ſtop to any ſuch Meetings.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151570:14"/> 14. Thirdly, Altho' any number, and of any men whatſoever, may Lawfully aſſemble together, whenſoever it is for a good end, and no evil Conſequence of ſuch a Meeting is foreſeen, or juſtly to be ſuſpected; Yet even <hi>The Biſhops and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters of the Church have no right to meet together as an Eccleſiaſtical Synod</hi> (That is to ſay they can have no <hi>Authority</hi> ſo to tranſact matters as to lay an <hi>Obligation</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others §. 1.) <hi>Except they have a Lawful Power and Commiſſion for their ſo doing.</hi> For whoſoever in any caſe, Acts without a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Commiſſion, may undoubtedly be <hi>Oppoſed</hi> by every man who is any way concerned in the matter; and may juſtly be obſtructed and hindered in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, by thoſe who have Lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority over them.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Here then, for the full and final de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of this Second Enquiry, let this Queſtion be propoſed, <hi>viz. From whence does an Eccleſiaſtical Synod, derive its Power and Authority, to ſit, and Act, as a Synod?</hi> In anſwer to which I take it Firſt to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plain from what I have ſaid §. 5. that Eccleſiaſtical Synods do not derive their Power and Authority immediately from God. For if they did they muſt be of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution. And Secondly as for the Civil Magiſtrate, our very Enquiry
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151570:14"/>ſuppoſes him, as yet, to have no hand in the matter. Thirdly then it muſt remain that <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Synods do immediately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their power and Authority</hi> (Antecedent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Civil Laws) <hi>only from the Church its ſelf: (Immediately</hi> I ſay; For that all Lawful Power and Authority whatſoever is <hi>Mediately</hi> and Ultimately derived from God I freely grant) For neither can we find any other perſon from whom imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to fetch the Power of ſuch Synods; Nor is it to be doubted but that (By vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of that Power which God has given to all men over themſelves) the Church may in ſome Caſes, Inveſt a Synod with an Authority over its ſelf; as well as the People, in their Civil capacity, may do the ſame thing by a Parliament.</p>
            <p n="16">16. The Sum then is this, that as Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Synods are of Human Inſtitution; ſo, antecedently to the Civil Laws, their Power and Authority is immediately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived only from the Church (As the Power of a Parliament is from the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their Civil capacity) And whene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a Synod is duly appointed by the Church, it has a right to ſit and Act; Nor ought it to be therein hindered or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by the Civil Magiſtrate; except he has juſt ground to believe that ſome ill conſequence will unavoidably follow
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151570:15"/>from their Sitting and Acting, which it is his duty to prevent. And let this ſuffice for the Second Enquiry.</p>
            <p n="17">17. The Third Enquiry contains two diſtinct Queſtions; <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt <hi>In what things;</hi> And Secondly, <hi>Over what Perſons may an Eccleſiaſtical Synod have Authority?</hi> (But ſtill antecedent to the Civil Laws.) And here I ſhall lay this down as a fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal propoſition <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>as no Aſſembly can have greater Authority than what is Originally lodged in thoſe Perſons by whom they are appointed and empowered; ſo neither can they juſtly claim or Exerciſe this Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but only in ſuch a meaſure or degreé, as it is Actually Communicated to them.</hi> Which being premiſed (And the truth thereof I take to be ſo evident as neither to need nor be capable of any proof) I ſhall from thence draw ſome very plain Corollaries in Anſwer to the Two Queſtions but juſt now propoſed.</p>
            <p n="18">18. And Firſt if it be demanded <hi>In what things may an Eccleſiaſtical Synod have Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority?</hi> From the Propoſition now laid down, I anſwer Firſt, That the Authority of an Eccleſiaſtical Synod cannot poſſibly be ſo great as to make that Doctrine which is falſe become true; or that to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Lawful which is againſt God's Law: For this would be to alter the very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151570:15"/>of things, or Laws of God; which Power is not in the Church, nor in all mankind taken together. Nor yet, Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, can they have any Authority to make that a part of Religion which Almighty God has not alreadly made ſo: For altho' the Modes and Circumſtances of Worſhip and Religion, may be ſettled and determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Church; Yet to make any thing become a part of Religion, that is to ſay eſſential to it, and thereby immutably and perpetually neceſſary to Salvation, is a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative that belongs to God alone. But Thirdly, in doubts or Controverſies, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning matters of Faith, or Points of Doctrine, an Eccleſiaſtical Synod may have Power to conſult, and debate the things in diſpute; and to declare their Senſe and Opinion concerning them: For this is no more than what may Lawfully be done not only by the whole Church, but even by any prudential Aſſembly of wiſe and good Men; there being no Law of God which forbids, or any way hinders them, ſo to do. But, Fourthly, when an Eccleſiaſtical Synod has thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined any Point of Faith or Doctrine; Their Authority cannot extend ſo far as to oblige any man either to believe the Truth of what they have ſo determined, if it be againſt his perſwaſion; or to profeſs it, if
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151570:16"/>he does not believe it to be true: The former of theſe being impoſſible and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Nature of things; and the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Unlawful, as being forbidden by God; And therefore both of them excluded by the firſt of thoſe Corollaries which I have laid down in this preſent Section. Fifthly, But if an Eccleſiaſtical Synod ſhall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine any thing in favour of an Errour, and even directly contrary to the truth; Yet if the Error be an Innocent one; that is to ſay contains nothing which is any way contrary either to the neceſſary Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith, or the Rules of a good life; altho' a man cannot be oblig'd to believe or profeſs ſuch an errour contrary to the convictions of his own mind; yet ſtill he may be bound in Conſcience to be quiet, and not to give any publick oppoſition to ſuch a determination; for fear of diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Peace, or breaking the Unity, of the Church thereby. For altho' every Chriſtian is required, according to his abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, <hi>earneſtly to contend for that Faith</hi> (i. e. that Religion) <hi>which was once delivered to the Saints;</hi> Yet for ſuch truths as have no neceſſary influence either upon Faith, or Practice, we are no where Commanded to contend: And if we cannot ſtand up for ſuch a truth without the hazard of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, or diſturbance in the Church; we
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151570:16"/>ought to be quiet, and permit other men to abound in their own Senſe, untill ſuch time as God ſhall think fit to bring their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to a better diſpoſition; and not to Sacrifice Peace and Unity, which the Laws of God require us carefully to maintain, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a truth as we are not Commanded to teach to others; or zealouſly, our ſelves, to contend for. And Laſtly if an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Synod duly empowered ſhall make any Decree to determine our <hi>Practice</hi> in any thing which is indifferent in it ſelf, and no way determined by the Law of God; from thence I do conceive will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe an undoubted obligation to Obedience and Conformity to be paid unto ſuch a Decree, which is ſo made. For if the Church, by a voluntary Agreement, might Lawfully lay a reſtraint upon themſelves in ſuch things as are indifferent (which no man I preſume will doubt) what can hinder but that they may give a power un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Synod to lay the like reſtraint upon them? For whatever Obligation People, of their own accord, may Lawfully lay themſelves under; The very ſame Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all intents and purpoſes, may cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be laid upon them by their Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives, duly choſen and Authorized.</p>
            <p n="19">19. Secondly if it be demanded <hi>Over what Perſons may an Eccleſiaſtical Synod have
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151570:17"/>Authority?</hi> From that Fundamental Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition which I have laid down §. 17. together with the Third Propoſition which I have laid down §. 15. theſe following Conollaries will evidently ariſe; which will make up a full Anſwer to it <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt that an Eccleſiaſtical Synod can have no more Authority than what is veſted in the Body of that Church by which they are empowered to Sit and Act. For the Church can give no more Authority than what it firſt has in it ſelf; Nor can a Synod, which is but a part of the Church, have any greater Power than what the whole is Originally endowed with. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, But whatſoever Authority is Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully veſted in the Collective Body of the Church, the ſame may by them be dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated to an Eccleſiaſtical Synod. For neither is there any thing which ſhould hinder ſuch a delegation as this; And where a Society is very numerous (as the Church is) it is morally impoſſible for it to exert and exerciſe that Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority which is Originally diffuſed throughout the whole Body; otherwiſe than by appointing and delegating their Repreſentatives to do it for them. As the legiſlative Power which, in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, is Originally founded in the Body of the People, could never be brought to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151570:17"/>any uſeful effect, if there were not appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Parliaments, or Aſſemblies of the Eſtates, on purpoſe to repreſent and Act for them. Thirdly, therefore it will follow, That an Oecumenical Synod may have Authority over the whole Church; but a National, Provincial, or Dioceſan One, can extend its Authority no farther than the People, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince or Dioceſs, for, and from which, it is appointed and choſen; Becauſe one ſuch Limited or particular Church is not veſted with any Power or Superiority over ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And, Fourthly, that the Authority of any Synod is greater, or leſs, according as it is given them by the Church which chuſes and appoints them: Provided that the Church does not pretend to Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate greater Power to them, than what is Originally veſted in its ſelf.</p>
            <p n="20">20. To conclude this point; As the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Paſtors of the Church, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive their Succeſſion down from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, have thereby a divine Authority communicated to them, to perform their reſpective Offices, and to teach and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern their reſpective Flocks, according to the Rules preſcribed by God's Law; From which no variation muſt, upon any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, be allowed of, or admitted: So is there no manner of Reſtraint laid by God either upon the Univerſal or any Particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151570:18"/>Churches; But that with a due ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination to his Law, they may, in all other things, which are not thereby already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for, manage and govern themſelves as other Societies do, by the Rules of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Prudence; And appoint their Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods or Repreſentative Aſſemblies to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree upon, and lay down ſuch Rules, as they think moſt neceſſary to be obſerved. And not only he who violates the immediate Divine Law and ſo continues without Repentance; but even he alſo who <hi>Obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately</hi> refuſes to be conformable to the Lawful and wholeſome Conſtitutions of the Church it ſelf; and thereby cauſes diſturbance and diviſion in it (which is as really, tho' not ſo immediately contrary to God's Command as the other) is juſtly to be excluded from the Communion and privileges of the Society. And ſo much for the Third Enquiry.</p>
            <p n="21">21. I proceed then to the Fourth and Laſt Point propoſed; <hi>viz. How far the right of Meeting and Acting of Eccleſiaſtical Synods, or their Authority over others, may be Reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Limited, or Qualified, by the Conceſſions of the Church to the Civil Magiſtrate; Or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the Laws of any Kingdom or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> And in order to the clearing of this matter, I ſhall lay down theſe two preli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary Propoſitions. Firſt that <hi>neither the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151570:18"/>Conſent of the Church it ſelf, nor any Civil Law whatſoever, can lay any Obligation upon the Church, or any part or member thereof, to do, or forbear any thing, If by ſuch doing, or forbearing, true Religion is any way ſo obſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or diſcouraged, as that God is thereby dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured, or the Salvation of men hindered.</hi> For neither our own voluntary Act, nor any Law that is enacted by an inferiour Power, can free us from an Obligation which is laid upon us by an Authority that is Superiour. But by the Law of God, which is above all, we are All obliged to promote the Intereſt of true Religion, and thereby both to advance his Glory and ſet forward the Salvation of other men. And therefore if we have conſented to any thing, or if the Civil Law has enacted any thing, which proves to be contrary to this Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion under which we beforehand indiſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly lay; both our conſent ſo given, and the Law ſo enacted, muſt be looked upon as void (I mean ſo far as they are thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to Religion) and all Obligations of this Inferiour ſort muſt ever be conſtrued with a tacit exception, that they, be not contrary to any former and ſuperiour Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation. But Secondly, <hi>If the Church Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, or any particular Church, ſhall conſent; or if, without ſuch conſent, the Civil Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of any place ſhall by Law enact or require
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151570:19"/>any thing which no way tends to the real pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice of true Religion, nor any way obſtructs either God's Glory, or Men's Salvation: Such a conſent ſo given, until it is duly revoked, and ſuch a Law, until it is by Lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority repealed, ſhall certainly oblige all ſuch as are members of the Church which ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, or Subjects of that Kingdom, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, in which ſuch a Law is enacted.</hi> For who can doubt but that any Society may, by general conſent, lay an obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon themſelves in ſuch things as are no way Unlawful? And as for the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Civil Laws; the command of God runs in the moſt general and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive terms, that <hi>Every Soul</hi> ſhould <hi>be Subject to the higher Powers.</hi> And that we ſhould <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to every Ordinance of Man:</hi> Nor does either reaſon or Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture furniſh us with any other Limitation of, or Exception to this Precept, ſave only that one of the Apoſtles, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.29. <hi>We ought to obey God rather than Men.</hi> Which ſufficiently proves that nothing can excuſe us from giving Obedience unto all ſuch Laws as are made by the Legiſlative Power of the Kingdom or Commonwealth, of which we are Members; Except it be that ſomething is thereby required which is contrary to the Laws of God.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151570:19"/>
            <p> From theſe two General Propoſitions, theſe following Corollaries, with particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar relation to Eccleſiaſtical Synods, do moſt evidently follow in Anſwer to the Laſt Enquiry; <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt That <hi>the Church may conſent, and the Civil Authority may, either with, or without ſuch conſent, Enact whatever Laws they pleaſe, concerning the calling; modelling, manner of proceeding, and Limitation of the Authority of Eccleſiaſtical Synods; Provided that nothing is thereby done which is prejudicial to true Religion and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety,</hi> Secondly, But <hi>if true Piety or Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or any part thereof, be really in danger,</hi> by the breaking in of Atheiſm, Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxy, or Immorality; <hi>And no other way can be taken, or found, to prevent or redreſs ſuch a miſchief, but onely the Aſſembling and free Acting of an Eccleſiaſtical Synod;</hi> Let the Civil Law ſay what it will; <hi>The Church</hi> (notwithſtanding any conſent of hers gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or pretended to be given to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) <hi>is bound to convene an Eccleſiaſtical Synod, freely to conſult and determine what is fit to be done for the redreſſing of ſuch evils as theſe.</hi> And (as Dr. <hi>Wake</hi> ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciouſly obſerves) If the Civil Magiſtrate <hi>ſhall ſo far abuſe his Authority,<note place="margin">Authorit. of Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>pag. 43.</hi>
                  </note> as to render it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the</hi> Clergy, <hi>by ſome extraordinary me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods to provide for the Churches wellfare;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151570:20"/>That neceſſity will warrant their taking of them. But</hi> Thirdly, <hi>If any other way may as effectually be found, for the preſervation of the true Religion and Piety; The Church ought by no means to break in upon the Civil Law; Nor to Aſſemble or Act in an Eccleſiaſtical. Synod, in any other manner than what is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to its Conſtitutions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. But if any man ſhall be ſo hardy as to demand, What Authority the Civil Power has to make any Laws at all in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical matters: Their proper buſineſs being only to ſecure the Peace, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the welfare of the people under them, in <hi>this World</hi> alone; and not to watch over their <hi>Souls,</hi> or direct them in the way of Eternal Salvation; which is the Office of thoſe of another Function; and, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately or immediately, ought ever to be the deſign of all Eccleſiaſtical Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: I anſwer; Firſt, that ſince Experience abundantly aſſures us how great an influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the due management of the affair of Religion, generally has upon the Peace and Temporal welfare of any People; I will follow that the Civil Government (whether it be heathen or Chriſtian) to whoſe care the latter is committed muſt needs be veſted in a Power of making Laws concerning the former; ſo far as is neceſſary for the performance of their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151570:20"/>Office, and the Execution of that Truſt which is committed to them by the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. And if the Temporal Magiſtrate at any time apprehends that differences a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion among his Subjects, may likely be improved into farther diſorders and breaches of the Peace, of which he is appointed the Supreme keeper and Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian; He certainly may (I mean with the concurrence of the Legiſlative Authority) enact and make ſuch Laws, as may beſt put an end to ſuch Diſcords, and prevent thoſe evils which thereby, tho' at ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, threaten the Civil State. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' he has no Power, by Virtue of his Civil Authority, to determine Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in Religion; Yet he may very Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully; And by his Office he is obliged to over rule and ſuppreſs all ſuch diſſentions about it, as are any way likely to prove injurious to the welfare of that Society which is committed to his Care and Charge. Secondly; Whereas it is very poſſible that Governours of the Church, may aſſume to themſelves more Power than what really belongs to them, and by degrees encroach upon the Authority of the Civil Magiſtrate, (as has actually been done by the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi>) It is Lawful for the Magiſtrate, in ſuch a caſe, to make ſuch Laws, as may effectually keep, and reſtrain the Church,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151570:21"/>within the proper bounds and Limits of it's own juriſdiction. For to ſay that the Supreme Magiſtrate has not ſufficient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to aſſert and maintain his Lawful Power againſt all Encroachments whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, is in effect to take away his Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and ſo to make him Supreme, and not Supreme, at the ſame time. Thirdly; If the Supreme Magiſtrate be a Chriſtian and a Profeſſor of the true Religion; It will be his duty to make uſe of that Authority, in which he is veſted, as much as he can, for the Encouragement of that Profeſſion of which he himſelf is. For he that has great Opportunities of doing good, and yet neglects to make uſe of them, is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable to God for burying that Talent, which he ought to have employed in his Maſters Service. Altho' therefore he ought not to <hi>Perſecute</hi> even a <hi>Falſe Religion,</hi> as long as it teaches nothing which is Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to Civil Society; Yet he may, and he ought, both to defend and encourage the true one. Which cannot, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, ſufficiently be done, without mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome Laws concerning Eccleſiaſtical affairs, as well for the ſupporting of the Churches Authority by the Civil Power, as alſo for the Correcting and reſtraining thoſe who are Unruly and Diſorderly; and under the pretence of Religion would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broil
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151570:21"/>the Church (And perhaps the State too) And cannot be kept in Order by her Diſcipline and Cenſures. And if the chief Stations in the Church ſhould happen to be filled with ſuch Men, as ſhould oppoſe the making of any ſuch Laws, as really would tend to the Security, Peace and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of Religion; I ſee no reaſon why the Civil Legiſlative Power (If in the hands of Chriſtians) may not, even with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the Church, enact ſuch Laws, and enforce them with ſuch proper penalties, as they are fully convinced would be really uſeful and ſerviceable to ſo good an end.</p>
            <p n="24">24. But here it may perhaps be demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſuppoſe the judgement of the Civil Magiſtrate and that of the Church ſhould, in this point, differ one from the other, which of them ought to take place? And put the caſe that the Church ſhould think it, at any time, to be abſolutely neceſſary, for the Glory of God and the good of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to hold an Eccleſiaſtical Synod; and the Civil Magiſtrate, at the ſame time ſhould refuſe his conſent, or directly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid them ſo to do; And that upon a ſtrong perſuaſion that the meeting of ſuch a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod would, in ſuch a juncture, be of very dangerous Conſequence, either to the Church it ſelf, or to the State, or it may
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151570:22"/>be to both; What muſt in this caſe be done? Muſt the Church convene a Synod, in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Conviction which ſhe has of the neceſſity thereof? And muſt the Civil Magiſtrate yield unto it againſt his own judgment? Or muſt the will of the Magiſtrate be obeyed and the Church act contrary to her own perſwaſion? To which I am able to give no other anſwer but this; That every man who is honeſt and ſincere will always act according as he is fully convinced to be his duty; as he ſhall anſwer for the ſame before the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of God: And if the different and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary perſwaſions of men do ſometimes occaſion ſome claſhing and oppoſition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, I know not how in this world it is to be avoided. But conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how both Reaſon and Scripture do enforce Obedience to the Civil Powers upon the Conſcience of every man; I think the caſe ought to be <hi>Exceeding plain,</hi> before Subjects ſhould offer, upon any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, to act contrary to the Laws of the Land: And when even their moſt neceſſary duty to God Obliges them ſo to do; yet ſtill it ought to be with all the reſpect and deference to the Civil Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate that the caſe will poſſibly admit of, that all juſt reaſon of offence may be avoided; and that the World may be
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151570:22"/>throughly ſatisfied, that it is pure Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience alone, and not any diſcontent or turbulent humour, which moves them to proceed in ſuch a manner. And ſo much for the Fourth and Laſt Enquiry.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:151570:23"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> Richard Sare, <hi>at</hi> Gray's-Inn-Gate <hi>in</hi> Holbourn.</head>
            <p>THE Authority of Chriſtian Princes over Eccleſiaſtical Synods; in anſwer to a Letter to a Convocation Man. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Appeal to all the True Members of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in behalf of the King's Supremacy. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Principles of the Chriſtian Religion Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, in a Brief Comentary on the Church Catechiſm. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Practical Diſcourſe againſt Profane Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Four by the Reverend Dr. <hi>Wake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Eſſays on ſeveral Moral Subjects. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhort View of the Profaneſs and Immorality of the Engliſh Stage. <hi>Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Defence of the ſaid View. <hi>Octavo.</hi> Theſe Three by the Reverend Mr. <hi>Collier.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maxims and Reflexions on Plays (in Anſwer to a Diſcourſe Printed before a Play call'd Beauty in Diſtreſs) Written in <hi>French</hi> by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Meaux;</hi> with an Advertiſement concerning the Book and Author. By Mr. <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier. Octavo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Gentleman's Religion; in Three Parts. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humane Prudence, or the Art by which a Man may raiſe himſelf, and Fortune to Grandeur. The Seventh Edition. <hi>Twelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151570:23"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
